A Guide to the Frank L. Robeson Papers, 1899-1952, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Frank L. Robeson Papers, 1899-1952, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2015-014
7.6 cu. ft. 6 boxes
The collection includes papers from Robeson's tenure as a student at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute, Columbia University, and Johns Hopkins University, as well as subject and research files from his nearly 50 years as an instructor and professor at VPI, dating from 1899 to 1952.
Robeson, Frank Leigh, 1884-
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Frank L. Robeson Papers were acquired by Special Collections prior to 2008. They are believed to have been donated to the library, probably after Dr. Robeson's death in 1974.
Scope and Content
The collection includes papers from Robeson's tenure as a student at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute, Columbia University, and Johns Hopkins University, as well as subject and research files from his nearly 50 years as an instructor and professor at VPI, dating from 1899 to 1952. The papers contain notebooks and students sketch/composition books; personal correspondence; research on topics relating to math, physics, and drawing; notes and lectures from classes taught; Virginia Academy of Science documents; papers; and publications; and a few photographs and negatives.
Biographical Note
Frank L. (Leigh) Robeson was born on June 24, 1884 in Farmville, Virginia, to George M. and Anna M. Robeson. In 1912, he married Mary Anna Matthews (1888-). They had 5 children: Helen (b. 1913), Mary (b. 1915), Martha (b. 1921), Amenta (b. 1922), and Andrew (b. 1927). Robeson died in September 1974 in Blacksburg, Montgomery County, Virginia. He is buried in Westview Cemetery.
Robeson graduated from Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute with a B. S. in 1904. Between 1904 and 1907, he served as an instructor in Mathematics and Drawing and later in Mathematics and Graphics. From 1910-1913, he was an instructor in Mathematics and Experimental Engineering. In 1913, he received an M. A. from Columbia University. From 1913-1917, he served as an Associate Professor of Physics and from 1917-1955 (except for a leave in 1922/1923) as a Professor of Physics. He completed a Ph.D. at Johns Hopkins in 1923 before returning to teach at VPI. Between 1036 and 1941, he was the head of the Physics Department. After retiring in September 1954, he was granted emeritus status. In honor of his long career at VPI as a student and teacher, the Department of Physics building, completed in 1960, was dedicated "Robeson Hall" in 1969. A portrait of him hangs in the building.
More on Robeson Hall:
http://www.phys.vt.edu/where/Robeson.shtml
http://www.vt.edu/about/buildings/robeson-hall.html
Sources:
An Historical and Genealogical Account of Andrew Robeson of Scotland New Jersey and Pennsylvania and of His Descendants from 1653 to 1916.
Find a Grave page
Arrangement
The original file names were retained when the collection was processed. Some related folders were consolidated and duplicates removed. The collection is arranged in chronological order with the undated materials in the last box.
Index Terms
Persons:
Robeson, Frank Leigh, 1884-
Subjects:
Faculty; Mathematics; Physics; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Machine Drawing Sketch Book, 1899 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Workshop Composition Book, 1902 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Notes and Papers, 1903-1921 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Personal Papers, 1904-1923 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Lettering for Engineering Students, 1904 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Notes, 1904-1915 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Electrical Laboratory Notes, 1904 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Notes, 1906-1913 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Transfer Notes from Loose Leaf Notes, 1907-1925 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Applied Mechanics, 1907 (Box-folder 1-10)
- M.I.T. - November, 1907 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Research and Reference Material, 1909-1926 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Relating to House Construction, 1910-1918 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Examples in Differential Equations, 1908 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Notes on Dynamics Text, 1910 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Technic of Mechanical Drafting with Notes, 1910 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Problems in Mechanics, Heat, Optics, 1911 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Notes on Osbourne's Differential and Internal Calculus, July and August 1911 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Correspondence, 1911-1920 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Columbia University Class Registration Book, 1912 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Modern Theories in Geometry, 1912 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Geodesy and Practical Astronomy, Columbia University, 1912 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Physics Laboratory- Freshman and Sophomore Instruction Sheets, 1913 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Partial Differential Equations, 1913 (Box-folder 2-6)
- Lecture Notes and Exams- 1st Physics, 1913-1916 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Notes on Astronomy, Heat, Differential Equations, 1913 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Notes, Articles, and Sketches on Homes and Homebuilding, 1913-1928 (Box-folder 2-9)
- Two-Story Apt. Building Guidelines, 1914-1921 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Relating to House Construction, 1914-1921 (Box-folder 2-11)
- W.F. Meggers- Electricity and Magnetism, 1915 (Box-folder 2-12)
- Physics 2 Exercises in Mechanics and Temperature Determination, 1916 (Box-folder 2-13)
- Clippings, Brochures, and Advertisements, 1916-1944 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Theoretical Mechanics- Notes from Lectures of Dr. J.S. Ames, 1917 (Box-folder 2-15)
- Experiments in Optics, 1917 (Box-folder 2-16)
- Physical Apparatus- to be Bought, to be Constructed, and where to get it, 1917 (Box-folder 2-17)
- Notes- Data for Text, 1917 (Box-folder 2-18)
- Physics Lab Equipment and Notes, 1917 (Box-folder 3-1)
- Notes and Exam Notes on Optics, 1917 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Exam on Optics and Experiment on Calibration of a Thermocouple, 1917 (Box-folder 3-3)
- Infinite Series Notes Theory of Function- Cohen, 1920 (Box-folder 3-4)
- Notes, 1920 (Box-folder 3-5)
- Residence Specifications, 1920 (Box-folder 3-6)
- Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box-folder 3-7)
- Research and Reference Pamphlets, 1920-1946 (Box-folder 3-8)
- Notes, 1920 (Box-folder 3-9)
- Einstein's Theory- Lectures of Dr. F.D. Miconaghan, Johns Hopkins University, June-July, 1920 (Box-folder 3-10)
- Moment in Inertia, 1921 (Box-folder 3-11)
- Lecture Notes and Exams- 2nd Physics, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3-12)
- Lectures on Electricity and Magnetism, 1922 (Box-folder 3-13)
- Electron Theory, 1922 (Box-folder 3-14)
- Vector Analysis- U. Chicago, 1922 (Box-folder 4-1)
- Lectures on optics, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 4-2)
- The Infrared Spectrum of Helium in Long Discharge Tubes, 1923 (Box-folder 4-3)
- Notes on Thermodynamics, 1923 (Box-folder 4-4)
- Introduction to Quantum Theory, 1923 (Box-folder 4-5)
- Sketching Book- Tables, 1923 (Box-folder 4-6)
- Atomic Theory, 1923 (Box-folder 4-7)
- Radiofax- Lefax Looseleaf Handbooks, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 4-8)
- Noteson Physics Laboratory- M.I.T., 1924 (Box-folder 4-9)
- Junior Physics, 1926-1937 (Box-folder 4-10)
- The ABC of Hydrogen Ion Control, 1926 (Box-folder 4-11)
- Junior Laboratory, 1926 (Box-folder 4-12)
- Constructed in Shop, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 4-13)
- Electricity and Magnetism, 1928 (Box-folder 4-14)
- Advertisements, 1929-1945 (Box-folder 4-15)
- Radio Talk, 1930-1946 (Box-folder 4-16)
- Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box-folder 4-17)
- Notes on Physics: Part 1, Mechanics, 1932 (Box-folder 4-18)
- Manuscript of Notes on Physics- Part II- Electricity and Magnetism, 1932 (Box-folder 4-19)
- Manuscript of Notes on Physics- Part I- Mechanics, 1932 (Box-folder 4-20)
- Notes on Physics Part II: Electricity and Magnetism, 1933 (Box-folder 4-21)
- Household Meteorology and Physics, 1934-1939 (Box-folder 4-22)
- E&M- Electromagnetics, 1935-1940 (Box-folder 5-1)
- Spectrophotometric Materials, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 5-2)
- Lecture Notes- Physics 312, 1935 (Box-folder 5-3)
- X-rays and Radioactivity, 1936 (Box-folder 5-4)
- Virginia Academy of Science, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 5-5)
- Notes on Physics Part III: Wave Motion, Sound, Heat, and Light, 1937 (Box-folder 5-6)
- Biophysics, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 5-7)
- Advanced Physics, 1938 (Box-folder 5-8)
- Biophysics, 1938 (Box-folder 5-9)
- E&M- Electrostatics, 1938 (Box-folder 5-10)
- E&M Laboratory Manual, 1939 (Box-folder 5-11)
- The Bent of Tau beta, July 1940 (Box-folder 5-12)
- Precision of Measure, 1940 (Box-folder 5-13)
- Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 5-14)
- X-rays, Spring Quarter, 1941 (Box-folder 5-15)
- Lectures and Notes, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 5-16)
- Physics 312 (Chemistry), 1942 (Box-folder 5-17)
- Notes on Mechanics and Wave Motion, 1943-1954 (Box-folder 5-18)
- Klystron Manual, 1945 (Box-folder 5-19)
- Schaum's Outline of Theory and Problems for Students of College Physics, 1946 (Box-folder 5-20)
- Paper: A Simple Method for Adapting on Ordinary Wall Galvanometer for use in Large Classrooms, 1946 (Box-folder 5-21)
- Electricity and Magnetism, 1946 (Box-folder 5-22)
- Electricity and Magnetism, 1947 (Box-folder 5-23)
- Correspondence (Box-folder 6-1)
- An Exercise on the Sphere of Geom. of Space (Box-folder 6-2)
- Electrostatics (Box-folder 6-3)
- Electricity and Magnetism (Box-folder 6-4)
- Illustrations of Stem Engines, Steam turbines, Pumping Engines (Box-folder 6-5)
- Manuscript Index to Notes on Physics (Box-folder 6-6)
- Negatives (Box-folder 6-7)
- Notes for a course in Thermodynamics (Box-folder 6-8)
- Photographs (Box-folder 6-9)
- Physics 3- Experiments in Electricity and Magnetism (Box-folder 6-10)
- Radiation (Box-folder 6-11)
- Thermodynamics, Second term (Box-folder 6-12)